all right
i'm joe and this is sean hi and uh yeah
we're gonna walk through
how a block gets executed so we're gonna
work in this module that's just called
executive as part of frame
and sean maybe you want to give us an
idea of like how this fits into frame
yeah absolutely so um obviously in this
frame folder we have a bunch of
different palettes and some of the
supporting like libraries and modules
needed to get
a frame working um executive is
not like the other palettes in this
folder because it's not a palette it
does not have declare module declare
storage
anything like that it instead has a
bunch of logic which is
um wrapped around what we assume in
frame
to basically allow you to execute and
run through the block process so when
you're actually writing some of your
code
in your different palettes um you have
things like you know
functions which may which may um start
at the beginning of a block
the actual execution of all the
different palettes like the ordering of
them
um and then finally things that might
happen at the end of the block and the
executive
module basically handles um all of that
logic
yeah so like as a runtime engineer
you're probably not going to be working
in executive yeah but it's good to
understand what it does
so that you know some of the functions
that are available to you and then also
like
the context that your um that your
dispatchable functions are being
executed within
yeah and i think one thing to point out
is that you know again you're not going
to be touching this very much but
understanding how it works is very
important because
um there may be things you assume about
your run time for example
that one function is or one palette will
always run before another palette
the executive module actually has the
logic in there which determines the
ordering of these things
so um you know we even i think at one
point had an issue where
we reorganized the order of our palettes
by alphabetical order
but this actually um killed some
assumptions in our consensus
layers which basically assumed that you
know one process would happen after the
other and so
it's important to understand maybe why
these issues might occur and how you can
avoid them
yeah um so yeah let's just start out
with like the uninitialized and on
finalized functions
yeah so um yeah i guess uh
missy the best place to probably look at
that um
is in another is in another palette um
anything i think what if instead we just
walk through like kind of just read from
top to bottom
to executive and then we can take a look
at maybe how that applies to a specific
palette yeah sure with the honest shows
yeah because
i mean the first thing that will happen
in terms of um any block being executed
is this on initialize but there's
some kind of steps that happen
beforehand the executive handles yeah
okay so let's i'll back up and like ask
a new
question all right so yeah let's get
started on like
first of all what is a block and then
what happens when this block gets
executed yeah so um i think blockchains
are actually quite simple objects to be
to be honest um uh they are composed of
these different blocks and these blocks
have like a set of transactions in them
and these transactions tell your
blockchain how the state should change
so these transactions may execute
different functions in your runtime
may execute different behaviors and
ultimately all of these things
may change an underlying state of your
blockchain and if everyone follows these
rules they all get to the same state and
we have achieved you know some form of
consensus so we can go
we can go through consistent process to
agree that we all have the same state
right
so like a block in substrate you know
has a header with some fields in it and
then the actual body of the block
is just a vector of extrinsic state
changes
and so the executive module is going is
the logic of how we execute
each of these extrinsics exactly um so
yeah let's start walking through it yeah
so i think um
one of the easiest ways to walk through
executive modules just by reading it
from top to bottom
actually follows a pretty common flow um
and i think it's pretty understandable
and readable
um so let's see let's start with yeah so
of course we have an execute block
function
and this is going to start the whole
process of you know like what's actually
going to happen you see actually calls
into another execute block
um we can go here we can see something
like you know um at the very beginning
of a block we're going to initialize the
block we're going to have to
manipulate things like with the header
right um
we're going to do things with digest um
digest uh i don't know maybe you have a
better explanation but it's mostly from
my understanding used in the consensus
it's like a um
i don't know some i guess i want to use
the word digest in my explanation of
digest but
um basically it's some some package
information allowing you to um
uh work with the different consensus
algorithms is that yeah i
actually don't have a great
understanding of it myself but i think
it's like it has like the slot number
the block author
yeah all the stuff that's like proves
that this block author had the right to
make this block
yeah again as a runtime engineer i
actually i've never actually touched
this myself
um maybe getting a consensus expert on
the show would be a great way to talk
about it but
um in my mind i think about it as these
are the things needed um in a block to
be able to
get to consensus about um what blocks
are valid um
okay we have the initialize block
implementation okay so this is the first
time we're gonna be seeing something to
be familiar if you're a runtime
developer
so if you're a runtime developer and
you're building a palette
one of the tools you have available to
you is this on initialize function
and the initialize function basically
allows you to run and execute some logic
at the beginning of every block so
this can be really useful for a number
of situations one i can think of top my
head is a storage migration so let's say
that you
introduce some new storage items or you
have some kind of change in your logic
which needs to
um assume this the storage is in a
different state you could actually
create an uninitialized function
so that the um right after your runtime
upgrade occurs we will actually go and
migrate some of the storage from
happening
or from one state to another state um
another situation you might be using on
initialize is just basically to do
anything at the beginning of a block
right like
there might be some kind of like
automatic timers like every five blocks
do this or you know in all of our
consensus stuff and staking we have like
in the session changes
and these other kind of things which
happen um on these cycles and so
um unlike the normal smart contract
world where basically all
um changes to your state must be
executed by a transaction
here we can have our blockchain
automatically execute some logic
on some kind of block based time cycle
yeah so you could put like a check that
says you know if
block number mod 1000 equals zero then
go do something else like every thousand
blocks you just want to go run some
process
exactly and so that's all controlled by
this on initialize and so
um you'll see that when you write um a
palette you'll can define an
uninitialized function and describe some
logic
and this line actually is doing some
clever stuff to be able to call all of
different uninitialized functions
and so if you actually take a look at
the syntax here it's a little bit funny
um but it says this is all modules as
uninitialized on initialize
and this all modules object here is
actually something that's generated for
you automatically
by the construct runtime macro so this
is where you list all the modules maybe
i can just jump to it real quick
just pull it up so people see it yeah um
but uh
what it does is basically it just has a
it's a it's a tuple of
all the different modules in your system
so if i go here and i do
search for a construct
run and i search go down yeah you'll see
here that
this macro has a list of all of the
different palettes that are included
in your runtime and basically um
it will also generate a bunch of other
objects to make things nice and easy to
work with
one of them is this all modules tuple
which basically lists all of the modules
and it will create that tuple
in order of these um of the list here so
if i have a different order of these
um these uh palettes it will actually
change the order of the tuple
and then when you go to the executive
and it's and it's calling this on
initialize it's actually
calling this function for each of the
different palettes
in this tuple in order yeah so it's
going to grab this all modules tuple and
go through and then check
does this have an uninitialized function
and if it does then it's going to
execute it
exactly and so when i was mentioning
earlier before about you know like
the ordering matters you know here if
you assume okay well this function must
be initialized before this function runs
you need to make sure that in your um uh
in your
uh construct run time that you have the
correct ordering right yeah so
initialize so this is the magic where
you know at the beginning of block on
initialize happens
um register extra weight unchecked
i actually don't know what this does um
but it seems oh it seems to
weigh oh maybe this is okay this is
probably this is actually new code
relatively speaking that i've seen but
it seems to me from what i'm reading
here that it may be telling us the
weight
of the uninitialized function so here um
you know whenever we do a transaction we
want to um make sure that the right fees
are being paid and also that our
our block can handle all of the weight
of the different transactions
yeah so this is like it's weighing all
the uninitialized and then you can see
right after it's
weighing on finalized so that it knows
how many more
functions it can put into this block
exactly so this is yeah this is actually
relatively new code to me but um this
makes a lot of sense right basically we
want to make sure that whatever
um pallets we're including that for that
block that it can handle
um all the uninitialized and all files
all the automatic logic before we
actually start doing transaction stuff
yeah sure
that's so this is perfect it makes sense
and um to have it here
okay so then we have some initial checks
um initial checks are checking things
like the extrinsic route so like you
know is that um is the
the block where um the the parent block
match the extrinsic group that we have
in our um
system right we're checking these things
are equal the tree must be valid that
all makes sense right basic consensus
things
and then we actually go and execute the
block okay so when we execute the block
of course we do the initialize block
that's what we kind of showed up here
with this um
this code then we also do any initial
checks
um i think initial checks should i think
we already passed it oh yeah okay so
this is the initial checks here exactly
um and then finally we actually execute
the extrinsics
with bookkeeping so here we're actually
going through um the individual
extrinsics this vector
and we're actually going to execute each
one of them yeah and you can see like
the line just before that
um this block.deconstruct function you
have
just like we said before you have a
header and then extrinsics and this
extrinsics it's just a vector so um you
have a vac and then a bunch of
extrinsics in it and it's just going to
go through and execute these
one by one exactly and so yeah so we see
we iterate through them
for each of them we apply the extrinsic
um with no note
um yeah and you can see here this this
is the i'm going to jump down to the pi
extrinsic
and you can see here that it basically
um yeah i mean
in short terms it actually runs the
extrinsic and will return to us whether
or not it had some
we returned okay or had error
um and then of course uh let's see what
we got here
um we do any final checks and so final
checks is kind of where we expect to see
um our final thing i think this
execution
actually should be touching this
finalized block logic so let me actually
walk through it
where is this finalized block happening
maybe one second it might be called
outside of this
oh yeah it might be cold outside of this
that's interesting okay
this this might have changed a little
bit since i last seen it but i i guess
at some
i would assume that after the execute
extrinsics with bookkeeping
um this is where the on finalized logic
will actually run
yeah so this is just like uninitialized
except kind of the other end
yeah at the end of the block and you can
see here yeah it's just exactly that
thing so one thing to
take note of here is that um we have
this all modules tuple
which is calling the on finalize and we
even had that up here
with the on initialize right but you can
see here the system module actually
has um custom code written into it right
so like
here um we have some custom code we
expect from the system module like the
note finished extrinsic
um which is being called directly in
system module so it's not part of this
normal like queue like all the other
palettes and so this is kind of why uh
system is different than the other
palettes it's a it's a frame it's a part
of the framework and it's assumed in our
executive that
um our system is implemented a certain
way versus all the other palettes gonna
have this more generic api which can
kind of get
pulled into this hook right that makes
sense yeah
um yeah and so uh
after we do the on finalize stuff um we
do any final checks i think the final
checks are basically making sure like
okay does um the final
uh uh out the state of our blockchain
after executing extrinsic match
you know all the things that we would
expect would it come to consensus if we
were to share this thing around
um and yeah it's really it's really not
that uh that not complicated overall i
think um you'd have to jump around a
little bit in this code but if you walk
that path you know we're really just
initializing the block
executing the block finalizing the block
yeah and one thing like to be careful
with here is this um
this naming finalized we don't mean
consensus finalized like it's in the
final chain
um in this context final like on
finalize
this just means at the end of the block
yeah exactly this is finalizing the
block construction
um but not actually finality in the
sense of like it's in the canonical
chain
yeah um yeah that's all right maybe we
can think of a better name
um so i think another thing to note here
is you know let's say that you wanted to
go
really deep into substrate so um of
course we make frame the easiest
platform to build new
uh runtimes with you know in these
different palettes but you know it is
possible to go
and touch and modify these this level of
code if you want to kind of diverge from
our framework
and i think you can see here how
powerful um
or how easy it would be to add
additional logic or
um you know code to the block
construction process so i'll tell you
for a while
we actually didn't have on initialize or
on finalize as part of
um frame and it's kind of through our
own necessity we added these things in
but you can see it's very simple to add
it in if you break down the block charge
process
to something simple like this something
that has very clear steps so
it's possible that you know if you think
of a good scenario maybe you want to
make a pr to substrate and introduce
other pieces of logic throughout the
different block construction processes
yeah and like one example that's not in
the executive module book
uh we have off chain workers right and
so like this is another thing that just
gets
called at the end of a block yeah so
maybe we can find that here off chain
worker yep so here's a
off-chain worker thing so this was
something that was again uses the same
kind of pattern that's all modules we
can assume that all of them
could have an off-chain workers logic
and we just run it right and then if we
actually go take a look
at maybe where this is actually run
i think i guess it also runs in a
different file here this is i think it's
run at the beginning of a block because
it gets called into this
yeah but it's not in this uh in this
in this file either way i guess the main
point is that you know
introduces like this was something that
happened very recently and
uh it's something that was possible
again because we have this really
clear and modular um platform for
basically just you know breaking down
all the steps of the blockchain and
these are the kinds of benefits you get
when
instead of building one specific
implementation of a blockchain you kind
of say okay with substrate we're trying
to build a generic framework for
building blockchains right
and we look at every layer and we try to
keep it as generic and as module and
extensible as possible
and these are the kind of benefits you
get when you do that so all of the crazy
engineering and substrate really comes
down to
making it simple and easy to extend and
modify
um the framework yeah um so to wrap up
what would you say are like the key
points for a runtime engineer here
yeah so one um you know you really
ideally shouldn't need to touch
executive
um you should understand how it works
you should know that um when you write
different um palettes that um what you
write in there hooks into executive
whether it's on initialize on finalize
or even the ordering of the palettes in
your construct runtime
um and basically yeah i mean just take
advantage of the fact that um
you know we kind of do a bunch of
automatic stuff the cueing stuff for you
and use that to basically make um
whatever logic is right for you in your
different palettes
great thanks sean yeah thanks